[Music]
any consumer looking on the internet for
a treatment for hair loss is exposed to
a multitude of remedies however we only
have good evidence for efficacy for the
fda-approved drugs finasteride sold as
propecia and minoxidil sold as rogaine
it's considered a myth that all the
patented hair loss supplements on the
market will increase hair growth and
they may actually be more expensive with
over-the-counter supplement regimens
costing up to more than a thousand
dollars a year whereas the drugs may
only be you know one to three hundred
dollars
the drugs can help but can cause side
effects the propecia can
diminish libido and cause sexual
dysfunction
while the topical minoxidil can cause
itching
though i believe this is a typo for
scaling
much better than scalping
here's a more comprehensive list of the
more common side effects to understand
why there are so many hormonal side
effects for propecia like impotence
testicular pain breast enlargement you
have to understand how the drug works
androgens
male hormones like testosterone
are the principal drivers of hair growth
in both men and women
we know this from studies a half century
ago that showed that castration of men
stopped hair loss
why exactly were they being castrated
due to eugenics laws in the united
states
when mentally handicapped persons were
castrated or had their tubes tied
against their will so-called
persons
were routinely sterilized without their
consent or knowledge and we
the united states of america was the
first country to introduce eugenic laws
which were later upheld by the u.s
supreme court
in the 1930s a vocal proponent
complained that the germans are beating
us at our own game
anyways
testosterone is the primary androgen
circulating in the blood and can be
converted to dihydrotestosterone
which is even more powerful by an enzyme
called 5-alpha reductase and that's the
enzyme that's blocked by propecia so it
inhibits the souping up of testosterone
that's why women are not supposed to
take it since it could feminize male
fetuses whereas for men it has the
sexual side effects like erectile
dysfunction which can affect men for
years
something the drug companies had to
disclose for the last decade
a difficulty in achieving an erection
that continues after stopping the
medication side effects that may even be
permanent
up to 20 of subjects reporting
persistent sexual dysfunction for six or
more years after stopping the drug
suggesting the possibility that it may
never go away
what we think might be happening is that
the drug may actually structurally
change the part of your brain
responsible for sexual function and
indeed though blood levels of hormones
and users with persistent effects appear
normal if you do a spinal tap and look
at the cerebrospinal fluid surrounding
their brains neurosteroid levels do
appear to end up being altered
so it's recommended that prescribers of
finasteride as well as potential users
be aware of the potential serious
long-term risks of a medication used for
a
cosmetic purpose
to date no new interventions are used
routinely in the treatment of male or
female pattern baldness
given the side effects of the current
drug options there's a need for
alternative treatments
so what about foods things we could eat
to combat hair loss
that's exactly what we're going to
explore
next
[Music]
you